Finding Aid for Don Binkowski papers, 1910-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Don Binkowski papers 1910-2013, 1958-1975
Binkowski, Don, 1929-
122 MB online
1 oversize folders
11 linear feet (in 12 boxes)
85807 Aa 2; Ac
District judge from Warren, Michigan. Correspondence, campaign materials, and other papers concerning his work as delegate to Michigan Constitutional Convention, 1961-1962, as Warren city councilman, and as attorney and judge; papers concerning local and state Democratic politics, and his activities with Polish-American organizations and his interest in Polish American history and personages. Also includes digital images.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Judge Don Binkowski (donor no. 5501 ) and came to the library in 1974. Periodic additions have been received.
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research, except for the diaries in boxes 10 and 11 which are closed until 2048.
Don Binkowski was born October 26, 1929 in Detroit, Michigan. He received his B.A. from the University of Michigan in 1951 and his LL.B. from Wayne State University in 1956. Following graduation, he worked for the Allstate Insurance Company as a casualty examiner (1956-1957), as assistant attorney general (1957-1959), as department officer in the office of the Michigan Department of State (1959-1960), with the Wayne County Friend of Court (1960-1961), as a delegate to the Michigan Constitutional Convention (1961-1962), and as a member of the Michigan Labor Mediation Board (1962-1963).
In addition to private practice in the city of Warren, Binkowski has served on the Warren City Council, (mayor pro tem 1965-1968) and as Judge of the 37th District Court in Warren (1969-1986).
Proud of his Polish heritage, Binkowski has been both a historian and a collector of historical materials relating to the contribution of Polish-Americans.
The Don Binkowski papers have been arranged into the following series: Biographical/Personal files; Constitutional Convention; Offices Held; Polish-American files; Political Activities and Elections; Visual Materials; and Schedule Book and Diaries.
The Don Binkowski collection consists of correspondence, campaign materials, and other papers concerning his work as delegate to Michigan Constitutional Convention, 1961-1962, as Warren city councilman, and as attorney and judge; also papers concerning local and state Democratic politics, and his activities with Polish-American organizations.
Subjects:
Binkowski, Don, 1929-; Busing for school integration--Michigan.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Judges--Michigan--Warren.; Macomb County (Mich.); Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan Federation, Citizens for Education Freedom.; Polish Americans--Michigan.; Warren (Mich.); Warren (Mich.). City Council.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Binkowski, Don, 1929-; Swanson, John B. (John Burley), 1925-1994.; Polish Americans--Michigan.; Politicians--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Biographical/Personal
  The Biographical/Personal files (3 linear feet) contain biographical information about Binkowski, including photographs and a photo CD, genealogical research, and correspondence with family, judges, and politicians. Digital content includes image files of a 2006 event and various historical and Polish American figures.
  - Alexander Groesbeck Historical Marker 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - Binkowski Builders undated (Box 1)
  - "Binkowski Family Album," 1963 (Box 1)
  - Biographical Information
    - 1958-2006 (Box 1)
      (includes photographs and campaign materials)
    - Event and Historical Photographs 1910-2006, undated, .ZIP files
  - "Col. P.W. Norris: Yellowstone's Greatest Superintendent," (Box 1)
    - 2003-2011 (Box 1)
    - 2011 undated, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Correspondence 1969-2010, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Genealogy Research
    - Binkowski 1977-2011, 4 folders (Box 1)
      (include photographs)
    - Wojtowicz 1956-1994 (Box 1)
  - Judicial Activities 1972-2009 (Box 1)
  - Military Service 1955-2003 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1966-2011, undated (Box 12)
  - Speeches undated (Box 1)
  - "Tolerated But Never Accepted: Polish American Officials of Michigan and Polonia in a World Political Perspective"
    - 1982-2009, 3 folders (Box 1)
      (include photographs, mostly contain correspondence about book, which is authored by Binkowski, as well as copies of images used in it, but not book itself)
      (see also oversized folder)
    - Volume 2 2010-2011 (Box 12)
      (contains materials relating to book, such as correspondence, but not book itself)
  - Travels (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous undated (Box 1)
    - Poland Trip 1977 (Box 1)
    - Postcards 1983 (Box 1)
    - Wojtowicz, Helen 1997-2004 (Box 1)
      (Includes photographs)
- Constitutional Convention Files
  The Constitutional Convention files (1 linear foot) includes correspondence, reports, materials received as a delegates, some of the statements made by him to the Convention, and materials related to delegate reunions.
  - Correspondence 1961-1962, 10 folders (Box 2)
  - Education and religion 1961 (Box 2)
  - Pressure Groups 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Binkowski for Con-Con
    - Campaign Materials 1961-1962, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Press Releases 1961-1962, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Binkowski: Statements on Amendments 1962 (Box 2)
  - Con-Con Election
    - Election and Campaign 1961, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Wayne County results 1961 (Box 2)
  - Con-Con Report to the People 1961, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Memoranda 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous 1952-2013, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Wilkowski, Anthony -- Con-Con Support 1961 (Box 2)
  - Schedule Book 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Con-Con Reunion and delegates 1970-2004, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Constitutional Convention material 1978, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Offices Held
  The series (4 linear feet) is organized into three subseries: Assistant Attorney General, Judge, Michigan 37th District Court, and Warren City Council. Files include complaints filed by and against Judge Binkowski, correspondence, administrative issues, and Warren City Council minutes.
  - Assistant Attorney General
    - General 1957-1959 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Civil Service 1959 (Box 3)
    - Executive Reorganization 1959-1961, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - General 1962-1963, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Michigan Labor-Management Services Inc. 1962-1964 (Box 3)
  - Judge, Michigan 37th District Court
    - Complaints against Binkowski
      - Formal Complaint No. 26 1982-1983, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Handlos, Allen 1984 (Box 3)
      - Judicial Tenure Commission 1969 (Box 3)
      - Meizlish, Sheldon M. 1972 (Box 3)
      - Myslakowski, Raymond 1976-1982 (Box 3)
      - Nos. 81-1932 and 81-2071 1982 (Box 3)
      - Other 1971-1984 (Box 3)
      - Skotarczyk, Mitchell lawsuit 1980-1984 (Box 3)
      - Wisniewski, Frank J. 1981-1985, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Complaint by Binkowski
      - Macomb Board of Commissioners 1972 (Box 4)
      - Randall and Schmidt appeals 1974-1975 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence
      - 37th District Court Administrative Problems 1980-1986 (Box 4)
      - Character Witness, Statements of and requests for 1982-1984 (Box 4)
      - Judicial Tenure Commission 1980-1984 (Box 4)
      - Law firms other than Philip Green 1969-1983 (Box 4)
      - Law offices of Philip Green 1981-1984 (Box 4)
      - Related to Marrocco, W. Thomas, Warren City Attorney 1981-1983 (Box 4)
    - Press and radio/TV treatment of complaints against Binkowski before Judicial Tenure Commission 1981-1984 (Box 4)
    - Press Releases 1969-1972 (Box 4)
    - Reference File 1969-1974, 7 folders (Box 4)
    - Salary Dispute 1972 (Box 4)
  - Warren City Council
    - General 1963-1969, 10 folders (Box 4)
    - Warren Symphony Orchestra 1966-1967 (Box 4)
    - Mayor Shaw vs. Binkowski -- Civil Law Suit 1966 (Box 4)
    - Minutes 1964-1968, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Minutes 1964-1968, 30 folders (Box 5)
    - Minutes 1964-1968 contd., 17 folders (Box 6)
- Polish-American File
  The Polish-American files (1.5 linear feet) relates to local and national Polish clubs and organizations with which Binkowski was involved.
  - Advocates Club 1958-1975, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - American-Polish Century Club 1955-1969, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Nowicki, Leo J. 1969-1975 (Box 7)
  - Parisville, Michigan historical Marker (1st Polish settlement in Michigan) 1969-1976, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - PL 480 (Funds in Poland) 1974-1977 (Box 7)
  - Polish-American Chamber of Commerce 1959-1960, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Polish-American Cultural Foundation 1958-1965, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Polish-American Day 1978 (Box 7)
  - Polish Genealogical Society Award 2008 (Box 7)
  - Polish Studies Programs
    - Radzialowski, Thaddeus C. -- Polish American Studies Center 1977 (Box 7)
    - Saginaw Valley College Institute of Polish Studies 1977 (Box 7)
    - University of Michigan Polish Endowment 2009-2010 (Box 7)
    - Wayne State University Polish Exchange 1977 (Box 7)
    - Wayne State University (Agreement with University of Lodz, Poland) 1977 (Box 7)
  - Polonia Civic Association 1966-1975 (Box 7)
  - Pulaski Day Banquet Testimonial 1972-1975 (Box 7)
- Political Activities and Elections
  The Political Activities and Elections series (1.5 linear feet) is organized by the following subseries: Binkowski Campaigns, Issue Campaigns, and Political Activities. The Binkowski Campaigns subseries documents Binkowski's various campaigns for office and includes campaign materials, correspondence, and press releases. The Issues Campaigns subseries includes files on issues Binkowski was involved with, including Citizens for Educational Freedom. Political Activities includes correspondence, materials from state and local elections in the 1950s and 1960s in which Binkowski was involved.
  - Binkowski Campaigns
    - Macomb County Community College Election 1963 (Box 7)
    - Warren City Council 1964 (Box 7)
    - Warren Council Election 1967 (Box 7)
    - District Judge Election 1968, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Probate Judge Election 1970 (Box 7)
    - Probate Judge Election 1972, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Appointment of a Probate Judge 1972-1973 (Box 7)
    - District Judge Election 1976, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Issue Campaigns
    - Anti-busing campaign 1972-1979 (Box 7)
    - Citizens for Educational Freedom 1962-1966, 6 folders (Box 7)
    - Citizens for Educational Freedom 1962-1966, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Citizens for Educational Freedom (tuition taxes) 1962-1976 (Box 8)
    - Church and State 1961-1962, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Detroit -- Eastside Parks 1958 (Box 8)
    - Integration 1967 (Box 8)
    - Prayer Decision 1961-1962 (Box 8)
    - Reflectorization Suit 1961 (Box 8)
    - School bus Issue 1955 (Box 8)
  - Political Activities
    - 1958 Election, 1957-1958, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - 1962 Election, 1962 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence 1957-1966, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Democratic party 1960 (Box 8)
    - Frank Kelly -- Attorney General Election 1962 (Box 8)
    - Governor John Swainson Campaign
      - Nationalities Division 1962 (Box 8)
      - Schedule 1962, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Michigan Democratic State Central Committee Nationalities Division 1962-1963, 7 folders (Box 8)
    - Polish Groups -- 1962 Election (Box 8)
    - United Democrats of Warren 1960 (Box 8)
    - Young Democrats 1959-1960 (Box 8)
    - Zolton Ferency -- County Prosecutor Race 1960 (Box 8)
- Visual materials
  The Visual materials series (0.2 linear feet) includes personal photographs of Binkowski's family and from his political campaigns. Also a VHS relating to a book written by Binkowski "Col. P.W. Norris, Yellowstone's Greatest Superintendent."
  - Photographs
    - Constitutional Hall Dedication 2001 (Box 9)
    - Dedication of the Governor Alex J. Groesbeck historical marker 1975 (Box 9)
      (include photos of Gov. G. Mennen Williams)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
    - Portraits and with family (Box 9)
    - Polish groups (Box 9)
      (with Governor John Swainson)
    - Political campaigns (Box 9)
    - Travels (Box 9)
  - "Col. P.W. Norris, Yellowstone's Greatest Superintendent", 1 VHS tape (Box 9)
- Diaries and Schedule Books
  The Schedule Books and Diaries series (2 linear feet) consists of 40 years of Binkowski's diaries and schedule books. The volumes are closed to researchers until January 1, 2048.
  - 1963-1988, 17 volumes (Box 10)
    [Closed until January 1, 2048 ]
  - 1990-2006, 17 volumes (Box 11)
Related Material
Additional material related to Binkowski's interest in Democratic politics and the Polish American community in Michigan can be found in another collection titled, "Don Binkowski, collected materials."